Guide to the Patriotic Envelope Collection [1861-1865], 1898 PR 117
New-York Historical Society
Patriotic envelope collection
[1861-1865], 1898
New-York Historical Society
PR 117
2.6 Linear feet (9 Boxes)
Patriotic printed envelopes, dating from the Civil War and the Spanish American War. Civil War examples include both Union and Confederate envelopes, with several hundred by New York printer Charles Magnus. The Civil War envelopes have been digitized and are available in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Varioius donors.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital copies of the Civil War envelopes are available in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
Arrangement
Within series, the collection is organized alphabetically by subject.
Listed subjects for Civil War envelopes are: African-Americans, American eagle, animals, U.S. Constitution, death, flags, foreign affairs, Fort Sumter, Liberty/Columbia, monuments, Satan, ships, soldiers and sailors, states (further divided by Union, Border, and Confederate), portraits (arranged alphabetically), U.S. shield, U.S. star, Unlce Sam, women, Zouaves, and miscellaneous images (further divided by Union, secession and Confederate scenes). Envelopes printed by Charles Magnus are kept together, and are further divided by American eagles, camp scenes, soldiers and sailors, cities, states, portraits and the Star Spangled Banner. A few oversize envelopes include images of camp scenes and flags.
Spanish American War envelopes are organized by portrait and then by subject.
Series I: Civil War Envelopes
Series II: Spanish American War Envelopes
Historical Note
The printed envelope came into use in America in 1840 and was first used for advertising or satirical purposes. In the 1850s to 1860s 'corner cards,' with printing applied in the upper left-hand side of the front of the envelope, were common. By the onset of the Civil War, printed envelopes were already in use as a propaganda medium. Lithography was the main mode of printing used for envelopes, especially for colored designs. Printed envelopes were sold either as a single item or with matching paper.
New York City was considered the printing capital of the United States from about 1825 and continued to be so during the Civil War years. Despite New York's official status as a Union state, many residents of New York City were not so assuredly in favor of the Union, or even of the war itself. In 1863 the city saw riots in Union Square and elsewhere protesting the draft and other war hardships. Such commotion in the nation's biggest city may have added more weight to the need for distribution of pro-Union propaganda. Printed envelopes continued to be popular throughout the century, and patriotic envelopes were printed once again during the Spanish American War in 1898.
Many envelopes in the Civil War series were printed by Charles Magnus, a prominent New York City lithographer. Magnus came to the United States from Germany following the political upheavals in Europe in 1848. He was an accomplished lithographer, and developed a following of customers who purchased his many printed products - maps, games, lettersheets, and artistic prints as well as political envelopes.
Related Materials
Many collections at the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections include Civil War-era material. These include the Stereograph File (PR 055), the Poster File (PR 055), the Album File (PR 002), the Caricature and Cartoon File (PR 010), the Portrait File (PR 052), War of the Rebellion Albums (PR 088), the Subject File (PR 068), and the Matthew Brady Studio Collection (PR 085). In 2000, many of the holdings from these collections were digitized and can be viewed as part of the Library of Congress' American Memory project, at "http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/ndlpcoop/nhihtml/cwnyhsarc.html." In addition, the Bella C. Landauer Collection of Business and Advertising Ephemera (PR 031) contains many further examples of printed stationery and other ephemera.
Spanish American War material can be found in the Album File (PR 002), Robert L. Bracklow Photograph Collection (PR 008), Burr McIntosh Photograph Collection (PR 041), the Portrait File (PR 052), the Poster File (PR 055), the Stereograph File (PR 065), the Subject File (PR 068), and the Playing Card and Game Collection (PR 115).
The New-York Historical Library and the Manuscripts Department also hold many Civil War and Spanish American War collections.
Scope and Contents
The Patriotic Envelope Collection spans the period from 1861 to 1898, with the vast majority dated between 1861 and 1865, and contains approximately 3,000 envelopes with patriotic scenes and text printed on their exterior. It is arranged into two series: I. Civil War Envelopes and II. Spanish American War Envelopes. Most envelopes measure approximately 3 x 5 1/2 inches. The Collection was removed from the Graphic Arts File during processing.
The envelopes are printed or embossed with caricatures, allegories, slogans, and portraits relating to war events and personalities. The vast majority are Union-oriented from the Civil War; most were produced by New York printers. Some are quite crude; others are beautifully designed and executed, many are in color, with some even printed in gilt. Scenes or text appears on most of the envelopes in the upper left hand corner. Sometimes the printing extends across the upper front of the envelope, or to the verso. Several envelopes contain duplicates of the same image, often in different colored ink.
Oversize material includes a few pictorial lettersheets from each war, as well as oversize (often legal-sized) envelopes.
Civil War envelopes have been digitized and and are available online via New York Heritage.
Caricatures.; Envelopes; Ephemera.; Political cartoons.; Stationery; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Participation, African American.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Propaganda.; Beauregard, G. T. (Gustave Toutant), 1818-1893 -- Portraits; Butler, Benjamin F. (Benjamin Franklin), 1818-1893 -- Portraits; Davis, Jefferson, 1808-1889 -- Caricatures and cartoons; Dewey, George, 1837-1917 -- Portraits; Lee, Fitzhugh, 1835-1905 -- Portraits; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865 -- Portraits; Magnus, Charles; McKinley, William, 1843-1901 -- Portraits; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919 -- Portraits; Sampson, William Thomas, 1840-1902 -- Portraits; Schley, Winfield Scott, 1839-1911; Scott, Winfield, 1786-1866 -- Caricatures and cartoons; Shafter, William Rufus, 1835-1906 -- Portraits; Washington, George, 1732-1799 -- Portraits
- Series I: Civil War Envelopes, 1
  Arrangement Note
  The Civil War envelopes are arranged by subject, and have been assigned numbers within each subject (i.e., the numbering system is not simply consecutive, but starts over with each subject). To request an item, researchers will need to provide the subject, the box number and the item number.
  Envelopes are listed in the finding aid alphabetically by subject. The "Title" field lists the subject first, followed by a colon and text that appears on the envelope. The "General note" provides a description of the image on the envelope and, where available, the creator.
  Existence and Location of Copies
  Digital copies of the Civil War envelopes are available in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
  - African-Americans: Sam, where's massa Jeff's sogers dis morning? (Offsite-box 1, Item 36)
    General note
    Two African-American males holding hoes, talking to one another. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left.
  - African-Americans: I'm glad I'm not in Dixie! (Offsite-box 1, Item 43)
    African-American man wearing a tattered version of Uncle Sam's costume and dancing. White envelope with black ink. Image on left.
    Creator: Magee
  - African-Americans: Uncle Sam sends his bird after traitor Jeff. (Offsite-box 1, Item 38)
    Three African-Americans watch as Jefferson Davis is carried off by an eagle. Davis holds flag bearing skull and cross bones. Yellow envelope with black ink. Image on left.
  - African-Americans: What is you gwing to fite' for? (Offsite-box 1, Item 57)
    African-American woman doing laundry with African-American man standing beside her smoking a pipe. White envelope with black ink. Image on left.
  - African-Americans: The innocent cause of the war. (Offsite-box 1, Item 18)
    African-American man seated with hoe and loaf of bread. White envelope with black ink and applied color. Image on left.
    Creator: J. E. M.
  - African-Americans: The peculiar institution. (Offsite-box 1, Item 45)
    African-American man, seated outdoors surrounded by foliage. White envelope with black ink and applied color. Image on top-left.
  - African-Americans: Taking an observation from a dark point. (Offsite-box 1, Item 59)
    African-American man with Caucasian boy on his shoulders who looks through a spyglass and holds a bayonet. White envelope with black ink. Image on left.
  - African-Americans: I'se contraband (Offsite-box 1, Item 58)
    Head of an African-American man at the center of a ten-pointed star. The names of ten confederate states are inscribed on the points of the star.. Pink envelope with black ink. Image on left. Embossed decoration on seal.
  - African-Americans: [Man in chains being whipped.] (Offsite-box 1, Item 42)
    Man in chains on his knees, his arms held by another man who is raising a whip over his head. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left.
  - African-Americans: Come back you black rascal. (Offsite-box 1, Item 56)
    Caucasian man holding a whip and shackles calling after an African-American family as they flee toward Fort Monroe. White envelope with blue ink. Image on top-left.
  - African-Americans: Contraband barricade. (Offsite-box 1, Item 29)
    Battle between Union and Confederate soldiers. Some Union soldiers using tools as weapons. Beige envelope with red and blue ink. Image on left.
  - African-Americans: Black drop. (Offsite-box 1, Item 55)
    Head of an African-American man coming out through the top of a bottle labeled "black drop." Pink envelope with black ink. Image on left. Embossed decoration on seal.
  - African-Americans: By golly massa Butler, I like dis better dan workin' in de field for ole Sesesh massa. (Offsite-box 1, Item 49)
    African-American man polishing a pair of boots. White envelope with black ink. Image on left.
    Creator: Zahm, S. H. & Co., publisher
  - African-Americans: You had better get out dere, Massa Jeff. (Offsite-box 1, Item 1)
    African-American man taunts Jefferson Davis who is in a box labeled refrigerator. Yellow envelope with black ink. Image on left (vertical orientation.)
  - African-Americans: The "peculiar institution." The "peculiar institution." (Offsite-box 1, Item 52)
    The feet of an African-American. Yellow envelope with black ink. Image of left.
  - African-Americans: Map of the seat of war. (Offsite-box 1, Item 4)
    African American man, left, map depicting Maryland, Virginia, Delaware and the border of Pennsylvania, right. Key of locations in upper left corner.
    Creator: Harpel, Oscar H. (Oscar Henry), b. 1828
  - African-Americans: I'se just "seceshed" from Ole Massa, Yah, Yah, Yah! (Offsite-box 1, Item 23)
    African-American man dancing happily. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left.
    Creator: Gates, James, publisher
  - African-Americans: Judas vile betrayed his master, I betrayed fair liberty. (Offsite-box 1, Item 51)
    African-American man with knapsack walking away from a Caucasian man lynched from a tree branch. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left.
  - African-Americans: The result of secession. (Offsite-box 1, Item 34)
    Two African-American males having a conversation. One poorly dressed, the other in a top hat and fine clothes. Cream envelope with brown ink. Image on left.
    Creator: Magee, J., copyright holder
  - African-Americans: Contraband of war; or, volunteer sappers and miners from the "f. f. v." (Offsite-box 1, Item 9)
    African-American men with mining tools in-hand, volunteering to join the Union Army. White envelope with colored ink. Image on left.
    Creator: D. Murphy's Son
  - African-Americans: Bress de Lor, we am contraban. (Offsite-box 1, Item 28)
    American-American man and woman dancing. Beige envelope with brown ink. Image on left.
  - African-Americans: Southern currency. (Offsite-box 1, Item 48)
    African-Americans, carrying knapsacks, being called by the North Star. White envelope with black ink. Image on left.
    Creator: D. Murphy's Son, printer
  - African-Americans: Music by the "Contra-Band." (Offsite-box 1, Item 31)
    Three African-Americans playing instruments. White envelope with black ink. Image on top-left.
  - African-Americans: The latest contraband of war. (Offsite-box 1, Item 13)
    African-American man standing with a hoe in his hand. White envelope with black ink. Image on left.
    Creator: Upham, Samuel C. (Samuel Curtis), 1819-1885, distributor
  - African-Americans: One of the F. F. V.'s after his Contraband. (Offsite-box 1, Item 32)
    African-American boy clings to the leg of General Butler. Butler extends his sword to fend-off slave owner with whip and dog. Beige envelope with red and blue ink. Image on left.
  - African-Americans: Farewell to the good old times. (Offsite-box 1, Item 53)
    Horse-drawn cart carrying bales of cotton with one African-American male walking beside, two others riding on the cart. White envelope with black ink. Image on top-left. Embossed decoration on the seal.
  - African-Americans: [Slave escaping at Fort Monroe.] (Offsite-box 1, Item 26)
    Caucasian man with whip calling out to an African American man who flees toward Fort Monroe. White envelope with black ink. Image on top.
    Creator: Young, Lockwood & Co., printer
  - African-Americans: Where's Jeff Davis? (Offsite-box 1, Item 33)
    African-American male crawling on feet and hands, wearing stripes, and holding a whip. White envelope with brown ink. Image on left.
  - African-Americans: Wanted: a $15,000,000 loan for the C. S. A. (Offsite-box 1, Item 47)
    African-American boy looking at large sign seeking funds for the Confederate States of America. White envelope with black ink. Image on left.
    Creator: King & Baird, printer
  - African-Americans: Him fader's hope, him moder's joy, him darling little contraband boy. Him fader's hope, him moder's joy, him darling little contraband boy. (Offsite-box 1, Item 30)
    African-American baby being held up by Caucasian man. White envelope with red ink. Image on left.
    Creator: Hoyt
  - African-Americans: A king for the south. (Offsite-box 1, Item 54)
    African-American man dressed in a C.S.A. uniform with epaulettes, a sword, and a frying pan for a hat. He is barefoot and holds a bottle. White envelope with brown ink. Image on left. Embossed decoration on the seal.
  - African-Americans: The cause of all our troubles. (Offsite-box 1, Item 16)
    Bust of African American man with image of a plantation in background. White envelope with blue ink and applied color. Image top, center.
  - African-Americans: The persuasive eloquence of the sunny south. (Offsite-box 1, Item 46)
    African-American man bound to a pole being whipped. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left.
  - African-Americans: I wouldn't pull down dat flag, Massa George (Offsite-box 1, Item 6)
    African-American man attempting to stop a Caucasian man [George Washington?] from removing the American flag from a flagpole. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left.
  - African-Americans: Oh! Massa Jeff, dis sesesh fever will kill de nigger. (Offsite-box 1, Item 50)
    An African-American man visiting two others who are in bed ill. On the wall are advertisements for things including " Dr. Jeffy's concentrated bond plasters," and "The great southern remedy." White envelope with black ink. Image on top-left.
    Creator: Wells, John G. (John Gaylord), 1821-1880, copyright holder
  - American Eagle: In union there is strength. (Offsite-box 1, Item 16)
    American Eagle perched on two hands clasped together in a handshake. In the eagle's mouth is a banner bearing the motto. White envelope with blue ink. Image in top-left. Embossed decoration on seal.
  - American Eagle: The American Eagle coming down on the C. S. A. pirates. The American Eagle coming down on the C. S. A. pirates. (Offsite-box 1, Item 5)
    Enormous eagle claw coming down from the sky above several ships. White envelope with black ink. Image on left.
  - American Eagle: The first blood. (Offsite-box 1, Item 8)
    American Eagle in flight over text. Beige envelope with red ink. Image on top-left. Refers to attack on the 6th Massachusetts Infantry as it was travelling through Baltimore, April 19, 1861
    Creator: Wells, John G. (John Gaylord), 1821-1880
  - American Eagle with Flag: How our American eagle serves the secession rooster. (Offsite-box 1, Item 21)
    Eagle standing on American flag holding feathers in his beak of a rooster labeled "secession" who skulks away dripping blood. White envelope with colored ink. Image on top-left.
  - American Eagle with Flag: [Eagle in flight carrying American flag with its beak.] (Offsite-box 1, Item 2)
    Eagle in flight carrying American flag with its beak. White envelope with colored ink. Addressed to [Mipas White ?] Boston, Mass. Three cent stamp postmarked Jun (year?), New (York?)
  - American Eagle with Flag: [Eagle in flight with American flag and olive branch clasped in claws.] (Offsite-box 1, Item 7)
    Eagle in flight with American flag and olive branch clasped in claws. White envelope with blue ink and applied color. Image in top-left.
  - American Eagle with Flag and Shield: The war for the union. (Offsite-box 1, Item 29)
    Seal showing dead eagle on American shield, "pluribus unum" above and with flags and shield below. Image on left. Text "the war for the union" in stars and stripes on top-right. White envelope with brown ink covering most of recto.
  - American Eagle with Flag and Shield: [Eagle with American shield and flags.] (Offsite-box 1, Item 3)
    Eagle with wings spread perched on a quill of arrows with American shield and draped flags behind him. White envelope with blue ink. Image on top.
    Creator: Reagles & Co., manufacturer
  - American Eagle with Serpent: The destruction of the snake of South Carolina. (Offsite-box 1, Item 2)
    Eagle holds a dead snake in beak and another in claws as many smaller snakes slither in surrounding grass. American flag behind eagle with Andrew Jackson and John Calhoun watching from top corners. White envelope with colored ink. Image covers sheet.
    Creator: Orr, John William, 1815-188
  - American Eagle with Shield: The war for the Union. (Offsite-box 1, Item 29)
    Eagle perched on American shield with the word "liberty" below (left). The words "The war for the Union" in stars and stripes (right). White envelope with colored ink. Addressed to Mrs. George A. Andrews, [Great] Barrington, Mass. With notes.
    Creator: Harbach & Bro., copyright holder
  - American Eagle with Shield: [Eagle with American shield] (Offsite-box 1, Item 23)
    Eagle with American shield. Scene in background includes train and ship. White envelope with black ink and applied color. Image on top-left.
  - American Eagle with Shield: [Eagle with American shield.] (Offsite-box 1, Item 56)
    Eagle with wings spread perched next to American shield with ship in background. White envelope with black ink. Image on left. "Boston & NY" in pencil on verso.
  - Animals: Where is Beauregard? (Offsite-box 1, Item 56)
    Elephant carrying a banner saying "Where is Beauregard? " and wearing on saying "Express from Harper's Ferry." White envelope with blue ink. Image on left.
  - Animals: Secession powder for rats. (Offsite-box 1, Item 81)
    Two rats, Manchester rat and Paris rat, gnawing at a cotton bale. White envelope with brown ink. Image in top left corner.
  - Animals: Southern honor. (Offsite-box 1, Item 70)
    Grasshopper blowing bugle and holding a banner that reads "hum." White envelope with brown ink. Image on left. Embossed decoration on seal.
  - Animals: Secessionist. Secessionist. Secessionist. (Offsite-box 1, Item 18)
    Mule with Confederate flag draped over its back. White envelope with black ink and applied color. Image on top-left.
  - Animals: The game cock Secession, after the fight. (Offsite-box 1, Item 32)
    Cock with the head of an African-American and the names Davis, Beauregard, and Toombs written in its tailfeathers. White envelope with blue ink. Image on top-left.
  - Animals: The Union game cock and secession shanghae. (Offsite-box 1, Item 29)
    A rooster, standing beside the American flag, and a hen, standing beside a flag bearing skull and crossbones, face each other across a river. The Capitol building is visible far in the distance. White envelope with colored ink. Image on left.
    Creator: Robinson, Alfred S., publisher
  - Animals: Recruits wanted for the brave southern army. (Offsite-box 1, Item 1)
    A dog and a monkey dressed in Confederate uniforms. The dog plays a drum. The monkey has a sword drawn and a flag showing stripes and skull and crossbones tied to his tail. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left.
  - Animals: "The Secession Wolf" (Offsite-box 1, Item 93)
    Wolf in a suit kneels before Little Red Riding Hood holding the American flag. Yellow envelope with blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Animals: A queer chicken. (Offsite-box 1, Item 31)
    A strange bird-like creature with part of a peacock's tail, a devil's tail and horns, a bat's wings and a hooked beak holds the Confederate flag. White envelope with black ink. Image on top-left.
    Creator: Jas. Gate, publisher
  - Animals: In Memory of the S.C. (Offsite-box 1, Item 83)
    Serpent wrapping itself around a hangman's galley with a noose attached. An American flag also is wrapped around the galley as well. White envelope with blue and red ink. Image on left side.
    Creator: Mickley, J. P. stationer
  - Animals: Let the Sword of the Union first subdue the monster Secession, then the Dove of Peace may present the olive branch and the sun of prosperity will shine again. (Offsite-box 1, Item 85)
    A hand holding a Union sword emerges out of the clouds with a snake wrapped around it. A dove with an olive branch in its mouth rests above the hand. Sun rays come out from behind the clouds. Envelope of white paper with gray ink. Image on left side.
    Creator: Upham, Samuel C. (Samuel Curtis), 1819-1885
  - Animals: Mad Dog!! (Offsite-box 1, Item 50)
    A dog, with initials "J. D.," on collar and "secession" on back, runs with bayonets coming down from above. White envelope with black ink. Image on left. Embossed decoration on seal.
  - Animals: Meeting of Davis and Beauregard at Manassas Junction (Offsite-box 1, Item 97)
    Davis and Beauregard as animals with hats on. White envelope with blue ink. Large image on envelope.
    Creator: Ridenburgh, William
  - Animals: Jeff Davis on a scouting expedition. (Offsite-box 1, Item 65)
    A fox steals away in the night on a road labeled "to Dixie's Land," holding two dead ducks, one labeled "Tennessee," the other, "Virginia." White envelope with blue ink. Image on left.
    Creator: Magee, J.
  - Animals: When Southern fools depute an ass. (Offsite-box 1, Item 9)
    A braying ass wearing a lion's skin with a flag tied to it's tail. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left with text below.